Finding Aid for Lyman S. Parks Papers, 1962-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lyman S. Parks papers 1962-1977
Parks, Lyman S., 1917-
85370 Aa 2; UAm
Pastor of the Grand Rapids A. M. E. First Community Church, Grand Rapids, Michigan, city commissioner, acting mayor, and later mayor, 1971-1975. Mayoralty files, political materials, scrapbooks of career activities, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was donated by Rev. Parks in 1977 and 1978 (donor no. 6103 ).
The collection is open to research.
Lyman Parks was born in Princeton, Indiana on March 12, 1917. From 1936 through 1944, Parks attended first, Indiana State Teachers College, and then, Wilberforce University where he received his bachelor of arts degree (1944). Parks also attended Payne Theological Seminary.
After leaving Payne, Rev. Parks became pastor of the A.M.E. Church in Marion, Indiana. He followed this with pastorates in Richmond, Indian in 1947, Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1952, and River Rouge, Michigan in 1964. In 1966, Rev. Parks moved to Grand Rapids to become past of the A.M.E. First Community Church.
While in Grand Rapids, Lyman Parks first sought political office. In 1968, he ran for and was elected Third Ward Commissioner. Then in 1971, following the resignation of Robert Boelens as mayor, the Grand Rapids city commission appointed Parks to be acting mayor.
In 1973, after nearly two years of service in this position, Parks decided to campaign for the office of mayor on a permanent basis. In the election, he narrowly defeated his opponent Robert Boelens. In 1975, he lost his chance for re-election by losing in the city's primary.
The Lyman Parks collection consists mainly of files created and accumulated during the period of his mayoralty. Included are files on the many federal, state and local conferences that he attended. The correspondence files consist mainly of congratulatory letters. The best documentation of Parks' mayoralty will be found in his speech file and in the several scrapbooks from the years when he was in office. The collection also includes photographs, both portraits and photographs of public activities.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical and Personal; Correspondence; Mayoralty Files; A.M.E. Activities; Photographs; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; African Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; First Community Church (A. M. E.) (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Mayors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Municipal government--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Parks, Lyman S., 1917-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Calder Plaza (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Children.; City and town life.; Dwellings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Ferris State College.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Graduation ceremonies.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Mayors.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Plazas.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Streets.; Helicopters.; Little League baseball.; Mayors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Plazas--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Saginaw (Mich.); Southfield (Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Warren (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical and Personal
  - Resume (Box 1)
  - Vacation trip 1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1968-1978, 8 folders (Box 1)
- Mayoralty Files
  - Campaign material for commissioner and mayor undated, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Children's drawings (Folder 1)
    (located in UAm)
  - Children's greetings (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Bicentennial-Sesquicentennial Committee (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids city boards and commissions list (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids City Commission (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Convention Bureau (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Historic Preservation Commission (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Model Cities program (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Opportunities Industrialization Center 1975 (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids printed material (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids sculpture dedication (Box 1)
  - Inter-departmental letters, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of congratulations 1971 (Box 1)
  - Letters concerning election 1973, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Mayor's schedule
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - October 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Mayor's reports, press releases and proclamations (Box 1)
  - Michigan Conference of Mayors 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Municipal League 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - National League of Cities 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Sixth Street bridge (Box 2)
  - Speeches, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Trip to China 1975 (Box 2)
    (canceled)
  - U.S. Conference of Mayors 1972, 1975 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Sister Cities program 1975 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, Michigan Advisory Committee 1975 (Box 2)
- A.M.E. activities
  - Alcoholic Incentive Ladder Task Force 1977 (Box 2)
  - Annual Conference materials and miscellaneous 1974 (Box 2)
  - Founders Day 1967-1977 (Box 2)
  - Sermons
    - 1962-1976 (Box 2)
    - Undated miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Easter (Box 2)
    - Mother's Day (Box 2)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 2)
    - Christmas (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Area Center for Ecumenism 1976 (Box 2)
  - Interdenominational Ministers Alliance of Grand Rapids (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Calder Plaza (Box 2)
  - Celebrities and other public figures (Box 2)
  - Ferris State College (Box 2)
  - Groups, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Mayors Exchange Day
    - Southfield 1972, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - Warren 1973 (Box 2)
    - Saginaw 1974, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Portraits (Box 2)
  - Recreation and sports (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  (also loose clippings; also includes photographs and memorabilia)
  - July 1967-March 1968 (Box 3)
  - July-October 1973 (Box 3)
  - October-November 1973 (Box 3)
  - November 1973-July 1974 (Box 3)
  - November 1973-February 1974 (Box 3)
  - February 1974-March 1975 (Box 3)
  - January-September 1975 (Box 4)
  - September 1975-February 1976 (Box 4)
  - Loose clippings and other items from scrapbooks (Box 4)